Speaker 1: Hey all, Peter Zion here, coming to you from Colorado.
Speaker 1: We are about to do the thing that we do every three months on our Patreon system,
Speaker 1: and that's you guys can send in questions and try to stump me or get something really interesting answered.
Speaker 1: You just need to sign up for Patreon at the analyst level, send in your questions, and watch me squirm.
Speaker 1: Our next question time will be the 21st of November, that's the Friday before Thanksgiving,
Speaker 1: so hope to see you there, and make sure the questions are really, really awkward.
Speaker 2: Hey all, Peter Zion here, coming to you from Ranchera Creek in Yosemite,
Speaker 2: where I have my own personal beach and pool resort, quite refreshing and a little chilly.
Speaker 2: Anyway, today we're going to talk about Myanmar, which I'm going to, of course, make some of you say,
Speaker 2: what the hell is a Myanmar, and why would I care?
Speaker 2: Well, let me tell you.
Speaker 2: Myanmar is a country in Southeast Asia, sandwiched between the part of India that India doesn't like to talk about,
Speaker 2: and Thailand.
Speaker 2: It is, well, it's having a really nasty civil war again, has been for decades, honestly.
Speaker 2: And we now have news that on the 28th of December, the ruling junta, a military group,
Speaker 2: has decided that they're going to hold elections again.
Speaker 2: And this is important for the three reasons that you should care.
Speaker 2: Number one, if we are going to move into a world beyond China.
Speaker 2: The Chinese are dying, so we need to.
Speaker 2: But if we still want stuff, we need to build out as robust of manufacturing supply chains outside of mainland China as we possibly can.
Speaker 2: Myanmar can be a huge part of that.
Speaker 2: It's already part of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations,
Speaker 2: but unlike Malaysia or Thailand or Singapore, it's not particularly advanced,
Speaker 2: and Vietnam long since left it in the dust.
Speaker 2: However, all types of manufacturing that are going to be economically viable
Speaker 2: require multi-step manufacturing supply chain steps,
Speaker 2: something that some policymakers sometimes forget.
Speaker 2: And that means you need someone on the low end to do things like assembly,
Speaker 2: and Myanmar is perfectly set up for that.
Speaker 2: So if we're going to have a reasonable chance of still having manufactured goods in a post-China world,
Speaker 2: Myanmar would really help if they were part of the solution.
Speaker 2: That's one.
Speaker 2: Number two, like I said, there's a civil war going on.
Speaker 2: And because of that, you've got lots of secondary groups, minorities,
Speaker 2: that are basically massively funding their operations through the heroin trade.
Speaker 2: Well, in the past, when the military has given up power to central control,
Speaker 2: the war has died down, and some of the heroin production and smuggling has died down with it.
Speaker 2: So yes, yes, yes, Americans love their meth,
Speaker 2: and they love their fentanyl and their cocaine, but we like heroin too.
Speaker 2: And anything that constrains the supply, I would say, is a good thing.
Speaker 2: And then the third reason why it matters is China directly.
Speaker 2: If China is ever going to escape parts of its geography,
Speaker 2: it really needs another outlet to the world.
Speaker 2: Right now, its entire population is basically on the eastern coast.
Speaker 2: And just off the coast is something called the First Island Chain.
Speaker 2: Japan, Taiwan, the Philippines, Indonesia.
Speaker 2: Countries that are, for all practical purposes, informal, if not formal, U.S. allies.
Speaker 2: And so China has never, ever been able to punch through the chain in any meaningful way.
Speaker 2: They would take a navy as powerful as the U.S. Navy,
Speaker 2: which they are nowhere close, to even try.
Speaker 2: So, what about an alternative on land?
Speaker 2: Now, going through Russia sucks because it's, you know, Russia, and they can't be trusted by anyone.
Speaker 2: But Myanmar provides an opportunity to not only bypass the Strait of Malacca,
Speaker 2: but get closer to, say, the oil fields of the Middle East.
Speaker 2: So, in the past, when the military has been in control, relations with the Chinese have been pretty good,
Speaker 2: even though the Civil War boils right up to China's border.
Speaker 2: But when the military gives up power and the civilian authorities take over,
Speaker 2: then it's a little bit different, and generally China gets shafted, loses all of its investments,
Speaker 2: and Myanmar opens to the West.
Speaker 2: That's what happened about 12, 13 years ago when I was writing The Accidental Superpower.
Speaker 2: So, there's a section on Myanmar in that book.
Speaker 2: If, if, if, if, if, in December, real elections actually happen,
Speaker 2: I see no reason why that shouldn't happen again.
Speaker 2: So, having a military dictatorship in Myanmar is something that the Chinese actually like
Speaker 2: because they know who to talk to.
Speaker 2: They know that, you know, you don't have to change policy every election.
Speaker 2: Now, I don't want you to get overexcited here.
Speaker 2: Democracy in Myanmar looks different than it does anywhere else.
Speaker 2: This is a country where the Burman people are largely in the center of the country along the Irrawaddy River.
Speaker 2: To be perfectly blunt, the military is all Burman, and they're wildly racist,
Speaker 2: and that's one of the reasons why the Civil War is going.
Speaker 2: And the last time we had elections, and this woman by the name of Ayan Suu Kee won,
Speaker 2: who had been a dissident for quite some time,
Speaker 2: policy towards the minorities didn't change at all.
Speaker 2: The Burman are pretty nasty with all of the minorities in country.
Speaker 2: So, I don't want to suggest this is a once-and-done and not part of a process,
Speaker 2: but it would definitely be a step in the right direction.
Speaker 2: One more thing to keep in mind, almost unique in Asia, certainly in Southeast Asia,
Speaker 2: there is a river that goes right through the Burman Territory called the Irrawaddy,
Speaker 2: and it is one of only a handful of navigable waterways in the Asian landmass.
Speaker 2: So, not only would the skill set for manufacturing be kind of like a 1980s Mexico,
Speaker 2: you know, relatively low-skilled, relatively low education, but really, really cheap,
Speaker 2: you also have the possibility, because of the navigable waterway,
Speaker 2: of moving cargo back and forth really, really cheaply.
Speaker 3: So, from an infrastructure point of view, it would be really easy to build out Myanmar
Speaker 3: if the politics align.
Speaker 3: We'll find out in December.
Thank you.